♪Confessing to the moon in the rustling wind back then♪
♪จันทร์เคยแจ่มกระจ่าง♪
♪Like a boat being swallowed up among the cities♪
♪พลันแปรเป็นทะเลคลั่ง♪
♪Watching the flowers fall in unease worries and troubles fill my mind♪
♪ตระหนกฟังเสียงบุปผาโรย♪
♪Am I going to where I want♪
♪ทุกที่ที่ไป♪
♪To stay or to leave you decide♪
♪ด้วยการไปหรืออยู่ของเจ้า♪
♪Nations are different♪
♪ปฐพีกับแผ่นดินก็ต่างกัน♪
♪One without desire is one that is not alive♪
♪ฟ้าดินไร้ใจ♪
♪Looking at the sky side by side♪
♪ร่วมเคียงชมนภา♪
♪We've gotten closer with time♪
♪กาลเข้มข้นกว่าเวลา♪
♪One glance the city of Chang'an is bare♪
♪มองผ่านปราดเดียว♪
♪Among the ridiculous people and things is me♪
♪ในเรื่องราวเหลวไหลของผู้คน♪
=Episode 49=
=ตอนที่ 49=
I've summoned everyone again
ที่เรียกทุกท่านกลับมาอีกครั้ง
because I have something important to announce.
ก็เพราะมีเรื่องจะประกาศ
This is the legendary posthumous edict,
นี่คือพินัยกรรม
written by the late emperor himself
ที่เล่าขานกันว่าอดีตฮ่องเต้
after the Morning Dew Rebellion.
ทรงเขียนไว้ก่อนเหตุการณ์กบฏเจาลู่
All these years,
หลายปีมานี้
it has been sealed within a painting.
มันถูกผนึกไว้ในม้วนภาพมาตลอด
And now,
และตอนนี้
it has finally seen the light of day again.
ก็ได้พบตะวันในที่สุด
This posthumous edict
พินัยกรรมฉบับนี้
is the real one.
เป็นของจริง
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
But
แต่ว่า
there's more to it than meeting the eye.
ในเรื่องนี้ยังมีเงื่อนงำ
That is why
ดังนั้นวันนี้ข้า
I've summoned everyone here.
เรียกขุนนางทุกท่านมา
I need to explain
ก็เพื่อพูดเรื่องนี้
the secret behind the posthumous edict.
กับทุกท่านให้แจ่มแจ้ง
(Thirteenth Uncle, Prince Guang)
(อาสิบสามอ๋องกวง)
(My fifth younger brother, Prince Yi)
(น้องห้าของข้าอ๋องอี้)
This...
นี่
What's going on?
นี่มันเรื่องอะไรกัน
How is this possible?
เป็นไปได้อย่างไร
The posthumous edict
พินัยกรรมฉบับนี้
was written using special ink.
เขียนด้วยหมึกที่ทำขึ้นเป็นพิเศษ
The ink will never disappear.
ไม่มีวันลบเลือน
Only four words
มีเพียงอักษรสี่ตัวนี้
will disappear once they touch water.
เมื่อพบน้ำก็จะเปลี่ยนไป
Uncle, you have treated me with such kindness and virtue.
เสด็จอาปฏิบัติต่อข้าด้วยคุณธรรม
But the late emperor and I used you.
ข้ากับอดีตฮ่องเต้กลับหลอกใช้ท่าน
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Back then, before the start of the Morning Dew Rebellion,
ก่อนเกิดกบฏเจาลู่ครั้งนั้น
the late emperor was afraid that the plan might fail.
อดีตฮ่องเต้ทรงกลัวแผนการจะล้มเหลว
That's why he met me in private.
ลอบเรียกข้าไปพบก่อน
He wanted me to imitate Goujian.
ให้ข้าเลียนแบบโกวเจี้ยน
He wanted me to acknowledge Qiu Ziliang as my father
รับฉิวจื่อเหลียงเป็นบิดา
and inherit the throne.
เพื่อสืบราชบัลลังก์
Since the late emperor wanted to protect me,
อดีตฮ่องเต้ทรงต้องการปกป้องข้า
he had to let another person
จึงต้องเบนความสนใจ
be the centre of
และไฟโทสะของฉิวจื่อเหลียง
Qiu Ziliang's attention and hatred.
ไปที่คนผู้หนึ่ง
That's why
ดังนั้น
he chose Prince Guang.
จึงเลือกเสด็จอาอ๋องกวง
So that's the case.
ที่แท้ก็เป็นเช่นนี้
I was wondering why the late emperor
กระหม่อมก็เคยสงสัย
would pass the throne to me
อดีตฮ่องเต้ไม่ทรงชมชอบกระหม่อมมาตลอด
when he didn't even like me.
จะให้กระหม่อมสืบบัลลังก์ได้อย่างไร
After the Morning Dew Rebellion failed,
ตอนนั้นหลังกบฏเจาลู่ล้มเหลว
Qiu Ziliang
ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
didn't kill my brother.
ไม่ได้สังหารเสด็จพี่
Instead, he put him under house arrest.
แต่กักบริเวณพระองค์
And Brother
ส่วนเสด็จพี่
had urged me
ก็กำชับข้าเป็นพันครั้ง
to proceed
ให้ข้า
with the plan.
ดำเนินแผนการนี้ต่อไป
Uncle,
ส่วนเสด็จอา
you were always on a mountain retreat.
ก็เร้นกายในเขามาโดยตลอด
That's how you were able to escape the disaster.
จึงรอดพ้นจากเคราะห์นี้ได้
So, were you the one behind it?
คำพูดตอนนั้นใช่เป็นของพระองค์หรือไม่
Yes.
ใช่
I
ข้า
didn't completely agree
ก็ไม่ได้เห็นด้วยกับแผนการ
with the late emperor's plan.
ของอดีตฮ่องเต้ไปเสียทั้งหมด
I wasn't willing to let you suffer on my behalf.
ยิ่งไม่อยากให้ท่านต้องมารับความลำบากแทนข้า
That's why I ordered my men to spread the news.
จงใจให้คนไปป่าวประกาศว่า
I told them to say that you have to distance yourself from wars and conflict
ท่านได้รับการชี้แนะจากยอดคน
because you were instructed by a saint to do so.
ต้องการหลีกหนีการแก่งแย่งชิงดี
Using that to my advantage, I did live in seclusion.
ตอนนั้นข้าก็ไปเร้นกายตามสถานการณ์
Qiu Ziliang
ซึ่งทำให้ฉิวจื่อเหลียง
did stop hunting for me after that.
ไม่ลงมือสังหารอย่างโหดเหี้ยมจริง ๆ
So, we saved each other.
พวกเราต่างก็ช่วยเหลือซึ่งกันและกัน
Indeed.
ใช่แล้ว
If I were blinded by greed
หากกระหม่อมมัวเมากับผลประโยชน์
and inherited the throne using the posthumous edict,
อาศัยพินัยกรรมรับสืบราชบัลลังก์
I'm afraid I would be the laughing stock of the world
เมื่อใดที่ความจริงปรากฏ
once
บัลลังก์ของกระหม่อม
the truth has been revealed.
เกรงว่าคงจะกลายเป็นเรื่องขำขันของใต้หล้า
Uncle, that won't happen.
ไม่หรอก เสด็จอา
People often say that humans are unpredictable.
ใคร ๆ ก็ว่าใจคนยากคาดเดา
But Uncle,
แต่ว่าเสด็จอา
you only became who you are
ผ่านบททดสอบของปุถุชน
by overcoming such ordeals.
จึงได้สูงส่งถึงเพียงนี้
Today,
วันนี้
I summoned all of you here
ข้าเรียกขุนนางทั้งหลายมา
to witness this ceremony.
ก็เพื่อมาเป็นประจักษ์พยานด้วยกัน
I
ข้า
will select Prince Guang as the Crown Prince.
ต้องการแต่งตั้งอ๋องกวงเป็นฮ่องเต้องค์ต่อไป
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Uncle,
เสด็จอา
you deserved everything.
สิ่งเหล่านี้ล้วนเป็นสิ่งที่ท่านสมควรได้รับ
I will humbly accept your edict.
กระหม่อมรับพระบัญชา
Thank you, Your Majesty.
ขอบพระทัยที่ฝ่าบาททรงเมตตา
Long live Your Majesty.
ขอพระองค์ทรงพระเจริญหมื่นปี หมื่นปี หมื่น ๆ ปี
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
the new generals of the Shencai Army
แม่ทัพคนใหม่ของทัพเสินไฉ
have assumed command.
เข้าประจำตำแหน่งครบแล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Before this, Li Zening
ก่อนหน้านี้หลี่เจ๋อหนิง
was bewitched by Left Minister's Peach Blossom Jade Bangle
ถูกมอมเมาด้วยกำไลเถาเยาที่จั่วเซี่ยงมอบให้
and committed a grave mistake.
บ่มเพาะเป็นความผิดมหันต์
Official Li wrote a letter personally
ใต้เท้าหลี่ลงมือเขียน
to beg leniency for her sake.
หนังสือขอความกรุณาแทนนางด้วยตัวเอง
Your Majesty, please take a look.
วอนฝ่าบาททอดพระเนตร
I understand.
ข้ารู้แล้ว
You may leave.
เจ้าออกไปเถอะ
Yes, Your Majesty.
พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
I thought Han Ding...
หานติ้ง
Speak.
มีอะไรก็พูดมา
Wasn't Han Ding a traitor?
หานติ้งไม่ได้ทรยศแล้วหรอกหรือเพคะ
The Left Minister tried to bribe him.
จั่วเซี่ยงซื้อตัวเขาไป
I told him to outwit them with their tricks.
ข้าสั่งให้เขาใช้กลยุทธซ้อนแผน
So,
ดังนั้น
Your Majesty,
ก่อนหน้านี้ที่ฝ่าบาท
when you wrote a retirement letter for Uncle Huaizhi
เขียนหนังสือลาออกให้ท่านลุง
and sent me away,
ทั้งไล่หม่อมฉันไป
were all of those part of your plan?
ก็อยู่ในแผนการของฝ่าบาทใช่หรือไม่เพคะ
I
ข้า
was just afraid that I would die suddenly
กลัวว่าจะต้องตาย
like my brother.
เหมือนเสด็จพี่
If that happens,
เมื่อถึงเวลานั้น
I
ข้า
don't want you
ไม่ยินยอมที่สุด
to stay by my side
ที่จะให้เจ้าคอยหัวเราะเยาะข้า
and laugh at me.
อยู่ข้างกาย
Nonsense.
ตรัสอะไรเหลวไหล
You mustn't curse yourself,
ทรงแช่งตนเองเช่นนี้ไม่ได้นะเพคะ
understood?
รู้หรือไม่
The sons of the Qi Family,
ลูกหลานตระกูลฉี
it's either they are too young, or they are mediocre.
หากไม่อายุเยาว์ ก็ไม่ได้โดดเด่น
After much thought,
ข้าคิดอย่างยากลำบาก
I figured out that Uncle
ก็มีเพียงเสด็จอา
was the only one who could accomplish this task.
ที่รับหน้าที่อันใหญ่หลวงนี้ได้
And
อีกทั้งเขา
he stood up to my test.
ก็ผ่านการทดสอบของข้าแล้ว
That's why
ดังนั้น
I came up with that idea.
ข้าจึงมีความคิดนี้
That's not it.
ก็ไม่ใช่
Actually,
ความจริงข้า
I had that idea in my mind long ago.
มีความคิดเช่นนี้ตลอดมาอยู่แล้ว
I just didn't dare to think about it.
ข้าไม่กล้าคิดลึก
I didn't dare to hope.
และไม่กล้าวาดหวัง
But now,
แต่วันนี้
I finally have the chance to do so.
ในที่สุดก็มีโอกาสนี้แล้ว
Your Majesty, you mean...
ฝ่าบาททรงหมายความว่า
Yu'er,
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
we can finally be together.
ในที่สุดเราก็ได้อยู่ด้วยกันแล้ว
I wish to spend the rest of my life
ข้าอยากจะใช้
with you.
ชีวิตที่เหลือกับเจ้า
You have suffered so much
เจ้าได้รับความทุกข์
because of me.
มากมายก็เพราะข้า
I
ข้า
will remember what you did for me forever.
ข้าจะจดจำไว้ตลอดไป
Now,
ตอนนี้
we can
พวกเราอยู่ด้วยกัน
finally be together.
อย่างเป็นสุขได้แล้ว
We can lead the lives we want.
ใช้ชีวิตอย่างที่เราอยากใช้
What day is today?
วันนี้วันอะไร
Your Highness,
เรียนท่านอ๋อง
today is the 15th.
วันนี้วันที่สิบห้า
It's the Lantern Festival.
เทศกาลโคมไฟพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
let me borrow her for a moment.
ขอยืมตัวหน่อยเพคะ
(Yan's Textile) Where are you bringing me?
ท่านจะพาข้าไปทำอะไรหรือ
What's wrong?
ทำไมกัน
His Majesty summoned me during the day.
เมื่อกลางวันฝ่าบาทเรียกข้าไปเข้าเฝ้า
He thanked me for my assistance.
ขอบคุณข้าที่วันนี้ช่วยอย่างเต็มกำลัง
He asked me about my requests.
ถามว่าข้าอยากได้อะไรหรือไม่
So, what are your requests?
เช่นนั้นท่านมีอะไรร้องขอหรือ
My requests?
ข้าอยากได้
First,
หนึ่ง
I want a panacea
โอสถวิเศษ
so that my looks can be restored.
ที่คืนรูปโฉมให้ข้าได้
Second,
ข้อสอง
I wish to travel around the Four Seas,
ข้าอยากไปเที่ยวให้ทั่ว
and have ample food and clothing.
อย่างไร้กังวล
Third,
ส่วนข้อสาม
I wish for a husband.
อยากได้สามีที่ถูกใจ
No.
ไม่ได้
You can't take His Majesty away from me.
ฝ่าบาทไม่ได้เด็ดขาดนะ
No one wants your emperor.
ใครอยากได้ฝ่าบาทของเจ้ากันล่ะ
Third,
สาม
I wish for a husband,
สามีที่ถูกใจ
a strong and healthy husband.
ร่างกายแข็งแรงกำยำ
Look at His Majesty.
เจ้าว่าฝ่าบาทของเจ้า
In just one year,
ในชั่วระยะเวลาสั้น ๆ แค่สองปี
from a strong warrior,
จากผู้ชายที่แข็งแกร่ง
he ended up in that state.
กลับเปลี่ยนเป็นสารรูปนี้แล้ว
Only a silly girl like you
มีแต่สตรีโง่งมเช่นเจ้าเท่านั้นแหละ
cares about him.
ที่อยากได้
Since young,
ข้าชื่นชมภาพ
I have always admired the prosperous state of the Xing empire.
ที่เจริงรุ่งเรืองของต้าซิงมาตั้งแต่เด็ก
I've seen the dances and singing during times of peace.
ชีวิตที่สงบสุข
I've seen
เขม่าดินปืนแห่งสงคราม
the flames of war as well.
ก็เคยเห็นแล้ว
Although it's a pity
แม้เสียดาย
that I wasn't able to witness a peaceful world,
ที่มาไม่ทันความรุ่งเรืองสงบสุขนั้น
I know that countless loyal officials
แต่ก็ได้พบประมุขผู้ปราดเปรื่อง และขุนนางผู้ทรงธรรม
and brave warriors had sacrificed their lives
ต้องมีผู้กล้าสละชีวิตมากน้อยเท่าไร
to produce such a splendid scene.
ถึงมีเวลาที่งดงามเช่นนี้ได้
I have
ชีวิตนี้
no regret in life now.
ไม่มีอะไรต้องเสียใจแล้วจริง ๆ
Yu'er,
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
thank you.
ขอบใจเจ้านะ
I'll return home tomorrow.
พรุ่งนี้ข้าจะกลับบ้านแล้ว
Take care.
รักษาตัวด้วย
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
the jujube cake I bought just now
เมื่อครู่หม่อมฉันซื้อขนมพุทรามา
was delicious.
อร่อยมากเพคะ
There's
ข้างหน้านั่น
an osmanthus cake stall in the front.
ยังมีร้านขายขนมกุ้ยฮวาที่อร่อย
Their cakes are delicious as well.
เป็นพิเศษร้านหนึ่งอีกด้วย
You should eat more then.
ถ้าอร่อยเจ้าก็กินเยอะหน่อยนะ
Let us buy more of them.
ซื้อไปมากหน่อย
Even if they're delicious,
ต่อให้อร่อย
we can't buy too many of them.
ก็จะซื้อมากมายขนาดนั้นไม่ได้นะเพคะ
We can visit this place
เทศกาลโคมไฟปีหน้า
during next year's Lantern Festival.
พวกเราออกมาอีกก็ได้
By the way,
จริงสิ
I think Han Ding has his hands full.
หานติ้งเหมือนจะถือไม่ไหวแล้วเพคะ
I've trained him for a long time.
เลี้ยงทหารพันวัน
This is the time for him to prove his usefulness to me.
ตอนนี้เป็นเวลาใช้สอยทหารแล้ว
Just let him hold them.
ก็ให้เขาหิ้วไปเถอะ
I
ข้า
wish to see the results of his training.
จะคอยดูผลการฝึกซ้อมทหารของเขา
I thought you loved the cakes?
เจ้าชอบกินไม่ใช่หรือ
Although I do love them,
ถึงชอบ
I can't consume them any more.
ก็จะกินมากมายขนาดนั้นไม่ได้นะเพคะ
We can
พวกเราค่อยกิน
enjoy them
อีกทีตอนมาชมเทศกาลโคมไฟ
on the next Lantern Festival.
ปีหน้าก็ได้เพคะ
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
what's wrong?
ทรงเป็นอะไรไปเพคะ
♪It's hard for an isolated force to hide the light rhythm♪
♪ทัพเดียวดายยังยากกลบทำนอง♪
I was just thinking
ข้ากำลังคิดว่า
that for the next Lantern Festival,
เทศกาลโคมไฟครั้งหน้า
I'm afraid
ข้าเกรงว่า
I will have no time to accompany you.
คงไม่มีเวลามาเดินเล่นกับเจ้าแล้ว
♪Is my heart♪
♪แสดงถึงใจข้าอย่างชัดเจน♪
But Yu'er, promise me this.
แต่อวี๋เอ๋อร์ เจ้าต้องรับปากข้า
Even if you're on your own,
ต่อให้อยู่โดดเดี่ยวคนเดียว
you need to travel happily
ก็ต้องเที่ยวเล่นอย่างมีความสุข
and enjoy the delicacies.
ชิมอาหารเลิศรสให้ทั่ว
♪Protecting the warm winter♪
♪ประกบมือรั้งไออุ่นขับความหนาว♪
♪Enjoying life with that longing♪
♪คิดถึงลมเมามายคราวสันต์♪
♪The golden dagger-axe releases the sunny sky♪
♪วางศาสตรามองฟ้าคราม♪
♪Enjoying half a day of escape♪
♪ขอเกียจคร้านครึ่งวันไม่ทำใด♪
All right?
ตกลงหรือไม่
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
did you forget?
ทรงลืมแล้วหรือเพคะ
I'm the best at both of these.
เรื่องกินดื่มเที่ยวเล่นหม่อมฉันชำนาญที่สุด
I promise you.
หม่อมฉันรับประกันต่อพระองค์
Even if I were
ต่อให้ครั้งหน้า
to visit this place by myself next time,
หากหม่อมฉันออกมาเพียงลำพัง
I would surely
หม่อมฉันก็จะนำ
share all of the delicacies with you,
อาหารเลิศรสไปแบ่งปันกับพระองค์ด้วย
all right?
ดีหรือไม่เพคะ
♪Why is fate secretly torturing me?♪
♪ชะตาไยเคี่ยวกรำจนช้ำตรม♪
♪One must learn to have compassion on women♪
♪ทว่าคงรู้จักรักหยกถนอมบุปผา♪
♪There are too many trivial times in this world♪
♪ปุถุชนยากหลุดพ้นพันธะ♪
♪Love and hate drags down those who aren't involved♪
♪รักและชังทำร้ายคนจนปลาในสระ♪
♪And the duckweed on the water♪
♪ซึ่งจอกแหนที่ผุดเกิดขึ้นมา♪
♪Is my heart♪
♪แสดงถึงใจข้าอย่างชัดเจน♪
♪Is like the mist and the sky♪
♪ดั่งเล็งธนูใส่หมอกควัน♪
♪Not in a hurry to disperse the wind♪
♪ไม่รีบเร่งเป่าพัดลมสลาย♪
♪I'll go into your dream first♪
♪ขอเข้าสู่ฝันท่านก่อน♪
♪May be nothing to the troubled times♪
♪แม้ด้อยค่าบนโลกา♪
♪Yet because of our believes♪
♪แต่ด้วยศรัทธาแห่งกันและกัน♪
♪Transparent and exquisite♪
♪ก็โปร่งใสงดงาม♪
♪The wind cuts a red thread♪
♪พายุกรีดผ่านแดงฉาน♪
♪The red thread cuts the wind♪
♪สีชาดตัดกลางหนึ่งลมคลั่ง♪
♪The feelings are already in my dreams♪
♪รักกลับจารึกห้วงฝันข้า♪
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
Your Majesty!
ฝ่าบาท ฝ่าบาท ฝ่าบาท
How's his condition?
เป็นอย่างไรบ้าง
Just as I expected.
เป็นเหมือนที่ข้าคาดไว้
His body won't be able to withstand it
การใช้พิษต้านพิษ
if we fight poison with poison.
จะทำให้ร่างกายย่ำแย่
Fight poison with poison?
ใช้พิษต้านพิษอย่างนั้นหรือ
Where's the source of the poison?
พิษมีต้นกำเนิดอยู่ที่ใด
It comes from the pill
อยู่ในยาทุกเม็ด
in every prescription
ในเทียบยาทุกใบ
I prescribed for His Majesty.
ที่ข้าจัดให้ฝ่าบาทเสวย
How dare you!
บังอาจนักนะ
Prince Guang,
ท่านอ๋องกวง
I was acting under His Majesty's order.
ข้าเองก็ทำงานตามรับสั่งของฝ่าบาท
Is there no prescription for me today?
วันนี้ไม่มีเทียบยา
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
you must stop consuming this medicine.
ยานี้ไม่อาจเสวยอีกแล้วพ่ะย่ะค่ะ
Although this potent medicine
ยาที่มีฤทธิ์รุนแรงเช่นนี้
is effective,
แม้จะได้ผลดี
your body won't be able to withstand its repercussion.
แต่เกรงว่าจะทำให้ร่างกายย่ำแย่
I understand.
ข้าเข้าใจ
But if I don't consume it,
แต่หากข้าไม่กินยาเทียบนี้
and if I only consume the Carefree Pill,
เพียงกินแต่ยาเม็ดสราญรมย์
just like its namesake,
ก็จะเป็นดังชื่อยา
I will not worry about anything.
ไม่สนใจเรื่องราวในโลก
I will muddle along until my deathbed,
ก็จะหาความสุขกับชีวิตไปตลอดกาล
am I right?
ไม่ใช่หรือ
Your Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
although fighting poison with poison
การใช้พิษต้านพิษ
may help you clear your mind,
แม้จะแลกกับการมีสติสัมปชัญญะแจ่มใสได้
it has grave repercussions for the body.
แต่เป็นผลเสียต่อร่างกายอย่างที่สุด
- You will only live for a few months. - Enough.
- พระองค์เพียงอยู่ได้อีกไม่กี่เดือน - พอแล้ว
Divine healer, heed my edict.
หมอเทวดารับราชโองการ
I order you to prescribe the same medicine.
ข้าสั่งให้เจ้าเขียนเทียบยา
Yes, Your Majesty.
พ่ะย่ะค่ะ
And
อีกอย่าง
you must not let anyone know about this.
เรื่องนี้ห้ามให้ใครรู้ทั้งนั้น
Until now,
จนถึงตอนนี้ฝ่าบาท
besides the medicinal soup,
นอกจากเสวยยาน้ำ
His Majesty has consumed 39 Ning Shen Pills.
ยังเสวยยาเม็ดกล่อมประสาทไป 39 เม็ด
Although the poison has spread to his lungs,
แม้พิษจะซึมเข้าสู่ปอดแล้ว
it has extended His Majesty's life as well.
แต่ก็ช่วยยืดชีวิตให้พระองค์ได้
Why?
เพื่ออะไร
Why did you do so?
ทำไปเพื่ออะไรกัน
For the Xing empire.
เพื่อต้าซิง
For a worthy death.
เพื่อให้ตายอย่างมีคุณค่า
You must think carefully.
เจ้าต้องคิดให้ดีนะ
If His Majesty dies
หากกินยาวิเศษเม็ดนี้ลงไป
after consuming the pill,
หากฝ่าบาทสวรรคต
you will be a regicide.
เจ้าก็คือผู้สังหารเจ้าชีวิตนะ
His Majesty,
ฝ่าบาท
I'm sure he will wake up.
ต้องทรงฟื้นขึ้นมานะเพคะ
You're awake.
ทรงฟื้นแล้ว
Yu'er.
อวี๋เอ๋อร์
Stop crying.
เจ้าอย่าร้องไห้นะ
You look better when you smile.
เจ้ายิ้มแล้วสวยมาก
Ever since you entered the palace,
นับจากเข้าวัง
you have smiled less and less.
รอยยิ้มของเจ้าก็ลดน้อยลงทุกวัน
Throughout my life,
ข้ามีชีวิตอยู่
because of Teacher's will,
เพื่อสิ่งที่อาจารย์ฝากฝังไว้
because of my brother's wish,
เพื่อปณิธานของเสด็จพี่
and because of the fate of the Xing empire,
เพื่อความเป็นตาย
I devote myself.
ของต้าซิง
I will die soon.
ข้าจะตายเมื่อไร
I don't know
ก็ไม่รู้
if I am a good emperor.
ข้าเป็นฮ่องเต้ที่ดีหรือไม่
You're a good emperor.
พระองค์ทรงเป็นฮ่องเต้ที่ดีเพคะ
Now, the people are living in peace.
ตอนนี้ประชาชนมีชีวิตอย่างสงบ
Their happiness knows no bound.
และสันติสุข
The state of the Xing empire is prosperous.
ต้าซิงเจริญรุ่งเรือง
Everyone is praising you.
ทุกคนต่างก็ชื่นชม
You did a great job.
ว่าพระองค์ทรงทำได้ดียิ่ง
But I'm really tired.
แต่ข้าเหนื่อยจริง ๆ
I have to calculate every step I make.
ข้าต้องคำนวณทุกก้าวที่เดิน
I don't dare to commit the slightest mistake.
ไม่กล้าเดินผิดแม้เพียงนิด
If the afterlife does exist,
หากมีชาติหน้า
in my next life,
ชาติหน้า
I hope I can live for my sake.
ข้าอยากมีชีวิตอยู่เพื่อตัวเองสักครั้ง
I wish to be a commoner.
ข้าจะเป็นสามัญชน
I wish to stay by your side for the rest of my life.
อยู่กับเจ้าชั่วชีวิต
It will happen.
ต้องได้แน่
That day will surely arrive.
ต้องมีวันนั้นแน่ ๆ เพคะ
In our next lives,
ชาติหน้า
we will be together.
พวกเราจะยังอยู่ได้ด้วยกันอีก
But Yu'er,
แต่อวี๋เอ๋อร์
I may not be able to survive for long.
ข้าอาจจะยืนหยัดต่อไปไม่ไหวแล้ว
I know.
ข้ารู้ดี
I know you don't want
เจ้าไม่มีทางยอม
to be imprisoned within the palace.
ถูกขังอยู่ในวังหลวงแห่งนี้แน่
So...
ดังนั้น
So, I will order Han Ding
ดังนั้นข้าจะให้หานติ้ง
to send you out of the palace.
ส่งเจ้าออกจากวัง
Going on safari is my favourite hobby.
ชีวิตนี้ข้าชอบล่าสัตว์ที่สุด
There are plenty of scenery
ยังมีทิวทัศน์อีกมากมาย
which I haven't seen yet.
ที่ข้ายังไม่เคยเห็น
Promise me.
รับปากข้า
You need to be happy for the rest of your life.
ว่าเจ้าจะมีความสุขกับชีวิตที่เหลือ
Go...
ไปชื่นชม
Go and explore the vast world on my behalf.
ทิวทัศน์งาม ชมจันทร์
Go and observe the stars and moon on my behalf.
ชมตะวันและดาราแทนข้า
I promise.
หม่อมฉันรับปากพระองค์เพคะ
Uncle.
เสด็จอา
Hold me up.
พยุงข้าลุกขึ้น
Uncle, have a seat.
เสด็จอานั่งสิ
I
วาระ
will die soon.
สุดท้ายของข้าใกล้มาถึงแล้ว
Fortunately, the eunuch's faction has been vanquished.
พวกขันทีถูกกำจัดแล้ว
There are many things waiting to be done.
ซากปรักกำลังจะฟื้นฟู
Prince Guang, heed my edict.
อ๋องกวงรับราชโองการ
My uncle Prince Guang is a man of great wisdom and vision.
เสด็จอาทรงมีความรู้กว้างไกล
He has experienced hardship.
มีประสบการณ์มาก
He carries to become a wise ruler.
เป็นอัจฉริยะวีรบุรุษ
I shall pass my throne to Prince Guang.
ข้าขอฝากฝังให้อ๋องกวง
With the duty bestowed upon by the seven ancestral shrines
รับสืบทอดบัลลังก์
and the duty entrusted by the world,
รับหน้าที่อันหนักหน่วง
this edict shall be carried out by the administration.
บริหารราชกิจ
Your Majesty, I will
กระหม่อม
humbly accept your edict.
รับพระราชโองการ
Uncle,
เสด็จอา
please rise.
ลุกขึ้น
Your Majesty.
ฝ่าบาท
♪One can never have enough of treachery♪
♪เล่ห์ลวงวกวนยลไปไม่เคยหน่าย♪
♪Old friends drink heartily, their past at their throats♪
♪มิตรเก่าอยู่ในเหล้าหอม♪
♪In my dream, you're next to me♪
♪ข้ากำลังฝัน♪
Your Majesty!
ฝ่าบาท
♪On the road to Chang'an at night, the breeze passes me by♪
♪ถนนฉางอันเมื่อคืน♪
Your Majesty!
ฝ่าบาท
♪The branch broke off, and me along with it♪
♪ผกาจากลากิ่งก้าน♪
♪Hold onto this melancholy, erase your doubts with more doubts♪
♪พะวงครานี้กำให้แน่น♪
♪Show me your love and sink my frustrations♪
♪จุมพิตข้า♪
Your Majesty!
ฝ่าบาท
♪Show me your love and sink my frustrations♪
♪ให้ความฝืนใจจมหายไป♪
♪To stay or to leave, you decide♪
♪ด้วยการไปหรืออยู่ของเจ้า♪
♪Nations are different♪
♪ปฐพีกับแผ่นดินก็ต่างกัน♪
♪One without desire is one that is not alive♪
♪ฟ้าดินไร้ใจ♪
♪Looking at the sky side by side♪
♪ร่วมเคียงชมนภา♪
♪We've gotten closer with time♪
♪กาลเข้มข้นกว่าเวลา♪
♪One glance, the city of Chang'an is bare♪
♪มองผ่านปราดเดียว ท้องฟ้าฉางอัน♪
♪Among the ridiculous people and things is me♪
♪ในเรื่องราวเหลวไหลของผู้คน แดนรุ่งเรืองแห่งข้า♪
♪Time goes on like the current, yet our yearning remains♪
♪กาลเวลาพาดผ่านเรือพันลำ♪
♪At the edge of the world, the sparks still live♪
♪สุดทางสุดขอบฟ้าควันไฟคุกรุ่น♪
♪Somehow the flower guides the wind throughout its journey♪
♪ไฉนบุปผานำพาสายลม♪
♪Can true joy end this dream♪
♪ความยินดีปลดระวางฝันครานี้♪
(On the 23rd of lunar March,)
(วันที่ 23 เดือน 3)
(Qi Yan passed away within Changming Palace.)
(ฉีเยี่ยนสวรรคตที่ตำหนักฉางหมิง)
(His posthumous title was Shizong,)
(มีพระราชทินนามว่า ฮ่องเต้ซื่อจง)
(and his body was buried within the Chang Mausoleum.)
(ฝังพระศพที่สุสานฉางหลิง)
(Prince Guang, Qi Chen, inherited the throne,)
(อ๋องกวงฉีเฉินรับสืบทอดบัลลังก์)
(changing the reign title to Pingzhong.)
(เปลี่ยนรัชศกเป็นผิงจง)
His Majesty has arrived.
ฝ่าบาทเสด็จ
Madam Jade is to receive the imperial edict.
อวี้เหนียงรับราชโองการ
Gods in heaven and earth.
เทพแห่งฟ้าดิน
Spirit of the sword.
วิญญาณแห่งกระบี่
My heart is like a sword,
จิตข้าเป็นดั่งกระบี่
suppressing the wicked and eliminating evil.
สยบทรชนขจัดคนชั่ว
My sword is like my heart,
จิตกระบี่เป็นดั่งข้า
protecting the nation and being loyal to the emperor.
ปกป้องชาติจงรักเจ้าแผ่นดิน
Please.
เชิญข้างใน เชิญข้างใน
Shopkeeper,
เถ้าแก่
give me another bowl of noodles.
ขอบะหมี่ข้าชามหนึ่ง
Right away.
มาแล้ว ๆ
Here are your noodles.
บะหมี่มาแล้ว
Sir, please.
นายท่าน เชิญทางนี้
Come.
มา มา มา
- We fortunately catch the opportunity. - Here are your noodles.
พวกเรานะ
Thank you, Shopkeeper.
ขอบคุณเถ้าแก่
Enjoy your meal.
กินเยอะ ๆ หน่อยนะ
If the late emperor
หากไม่ใช่อดีตฮ่องเต้
didn't cancel the Menyin official selection system
ยกเลิกการสืบทอดตำแหน่งทางสายเลือด
and introduced the imperial examination system,
เปลี่ยนเป็นสอบเคอจวี่
poor people like us
คนยากจนเช่นพวกเรา
will never be able to make a name for ourselves.
ก็คงไม่มีโอกาสเชิดหน้าชูตา
You're right.
นั่นสิ
Let's enjoy our noodles first.
กินหมี่ ๆ
Of course we only dare to sell our goods
ย่อมต้องเป็นวันเวลาที่สงบสุข
when the nation is at peace.
จึงกล้าลากของมาขายสิ
No one dares to go out
ในยุคสงคราม
during wartime.
ใครบ้างกล้าออกจากบ้าน
(Have you heard that?)
(ทรงได้ยินแล้วใช่หรือไม่เพคะ)
(Your wish)
(สิ่งที่พระองค์ทรงปรารถนา)
(has finally been realised.)
(ในที่สุดก็เป็นจริงแล้ว)
Shopkeeper,
เถ้าแก่
get me the bill.
คิดเงิน
Coming.
มาแล้ว
How much?
คิดหน่อยนะ
Four bowls? That will be ten wen.
สี่ชามสิบอีแปะ
All right.
ได้
Thank you.
ขอบคุณมาก
You're welcome.
ไม่ต้องเกรงใจ
♪Life is a dream how long do happy times last♪
♪ชีวิตล่องลอยดุจฝัน เคยสุขกี่ครั้ง♪
♪The sword can't break this karma♪
♪ชักดาบฟันฟาด กลับมิอาจสะบั้นเหตุและผล♪
♪Look how blurry and lonely the world is♪
♪มองฟ้ามองดินล้วนไม่ยินไม่แยแส♪
♪Still can't let go of this life as time goes by♪
♪ตะวันรุ่งจันทราโรย ชีพนี้ยังคงน่าถนอม♪
♪Even the iron and golden dagger-axe cannot extinguish the fire in my heart♪
♪ควบอาชาพร้อมอาวุธ มิอาจหยุดไฟในทรวง♪
♪Remembering the past and letting time while away♪
♪คิดถึงฝันในวันเก่า นานเท่านาน ยังคงเจ็บ♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪
♪The past is in front of you♪
♪อดีตพลันไหลผ่านสองตา♪
♪Forgetting while piecing it together♪
♪ทางหนึ่งเพียรลืม อีกทางเพียรจำ♪
♪Like when I sincerely put my hands together♪
♪หากข้าประกบมือประนมกร♪
♪I only wish that you can be saved♪
♪ไหว้วอนให้เจ้าได้หลุดพ้น♪